Guide to the W. Lloyd Wright papers, 1786-1945 MS2075
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
W. Lloyd Wright papers
1786-1945
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Wright, W. Lloyd (William Lloyd)
MS2075
3.5 Linear Feet
Collection includes correspondence, bills, receipts, lottery tickets, proclamations, testimonials, auction catalogue, newspapers, bonds, stock certificates, and checks. The material dates from 1786-1945. All of the material in this collection relates to prominent people and activities in Washington, D.C.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The W. (William) Lloyd Wright Collection was donated to the University by Wright's sister Mathilda Wright following his death in 1950.
Historical or Biographical Note
W. (William) Lloyd Wright (1876-1950) was a draftsman and engineer for the U.S. Navy, and a collector of manuscripts, photographs, and pamphlets.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection includes correspondence, bills, receipts, lottery tickets, proclamations, testimonials, auction catalogue, newspapers, bonds, stock certificates, and checks. The material dates from 1786-1945. All of the material in this collection relates to prominent people and activities in Washington, D.C.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Correspondence, Financial papers, and Miscellaneous.
Washington (D.C.) -- History; Photographs; Washington (D.C.); Social life and customs; Finance; Economic conditions; United States -- History -- War of 1812.; Seaton, William Winston; Royall, Anne Newport; Staughton, William; Payne, John Howard; Wright, W. Lloyd (William Lloyd); Corcoran, W. W. (William Wilson); William, Thornton; Georgetown University; Latrobe, Benj. H. (Benjamin Henry); Green, Duff; Greenough, Horatio; Jefferson, Thomas; Key, Philip Barton; Mills, Robert; Page, Thomas Nelson; Blodget, Samuel; Gales, Joseph; Bryan, W.B. (Wilhelmus Bogart); Riggs, George Washington; Douglass, Frederick; Ellicott, Andrew; Force, Peter; Custis, George Washington Parke
- Correspondence, 1795-1906; MS2075 Series 1; 2.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence that dates from 1795-1906. The 117 letters in this series are from prominent Washingtonians, such as W.W. Corcoran, banker and philanthropist, Peter Force, historian, printer, and member of the Washington, D.C. city council, and Horatio Greenough, an American sculptor known for his controversial statue of George Washington. Also included are letters from Joseph Gales and William Seaton (both journalists and mayors of Washington, D.C.), George Washington Riggs, banker and one of the founders of the Corcoran and Riggs banking firm, and Robert Mills, architect of the Washington Monument.
  - Adlum, John (1759-1836). Letter: Philadelphia, to Aaron Ogden, 1799 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Summary: Requests permission from Col. Ogden to take three weeks from duty to see to his farm duties. (Adlum was a vintner, and wrote a memoir on the "cultivation of the vine in America," which is in Special Collections, call number SB 389 .A28).
  - Baird, Spencer Fullerton (1823-1887). Letter: Washington, DC, to E.S. Morse, 1878 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Summary: Asks for an illustration from a book by Morse, to be used in a Smithsonian Institution publication. (Baird was Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution from 1879-1882).
  - Barber, Virgil (1782-1847). Letter: Georgetown College, to Silas Wood, 1820 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Summary: Sends information on a former Georgetown student; mentions planned move to Jusuits' house in Washington. (Barber was an Episcopal, then Catholic clergyman, who taught at Georgetown University).
  - Barlow, Ruth (1755-1818). Letter: to Pamela Jacob, Windsor, Vt., 1815 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Summary: Mentions arrival at Mason's Island (now Theodore Roosevelt's Island) on Oct. 22. Expresses pessimism about the ability of the U.S. to win the War of 1812. (Ruth Baldwin Barlow married poet and diplomat John Barlow in 1781).
  - Barlow, Ruth (1755-1818). Letter: Kalorama, to Pamela Jacob, Windsor, Vt, 1816 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Summary: Mentions long hours of business correspondence, her granddaughter, and her affection for Mrs. Jacobs.
  - Blake, George B. Letter: City of Washington, to Col. John S. Cunningham, 1874 November 09 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Summary: Argues that the true name of the capital of the United States is City of Washington, not Washington. (Blake was a member of the Association of the Oldest Inhabitants of the District of Columbia).
  - Blodget, Samuel (1757-1814). Letter: to Daniel Gilman, 1795 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Summary: Concerns financial dealings. (Blodget was a merchant, land speculator, and architect, especially in the early District of Columbia. He died bankrupt).
  - Bomford, George (1792-1848). Letter: Washington, to Gen. J. Manton, 1825 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Summary: Concerns transfer of artillery from New York state. (Bomford was a soldier, ordnance expert, and a resident of Washington, D.C.).
  - Burnett, Frances Hodgson. Letter: 1770 Mass. Ave., to Ms. Scott, 1894 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Summary: Apologizes for not writing before, says has been in England and has just returned because of son's illness. (Burnett was an author, especially of children's books, and was a resident of Washington, D.C., 1876-1898).
  - Causten, Anna Payne. Letter: Washington, to unidentified recipient, between 1809 and 1817., 1809-1817 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Summary: Mentions her Aunt Dolley Madison's severe cold and the visitors she received. Also mentions President James Madison. (Causten was the niece of Dolley Madison and lived with her in the White House).
  - Cooke, Henry David (1825-1881). Letter: Washington, to Richard Cruikshank, 1871 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Summary: Approves the use of a District of Columbia government building for the use of a public library. (Cooke was the brother of banker Jay Cooke and the first governor of Washington, D.C., 1871-1873).
  - Cooke, Henry David (1825-1881). Letter: Washington, to Gardner Rand, Troy, N.Y., 1873 October 02 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Summary: Sends his autograph and says he has resigned as governor of Washington, D.C.
  - Cooke, Henry David (1825-1881). Letter: Washington, DC, to Andrew J Rogers, Wash., 1873 March 07 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Summary: Tells Rogers he is unable to make an appointment, although he is in favor of developing the water power of Great Falls of the Potomac.
  - Corcoran, W.W. (1798-1888). Letter: Washington, DC, to Dr. James Laurie, Wash., 1843 January 04 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Summary: Mentions willingness to pay any balance outstanding on his account. (Corcoran was a Washington, D.C. banker and philanthropist).
  - Corcoran, W.W. (1798-1888). Note: to "Dear Madam", 1881 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Summary: Thanks recipient for sending account of the death of a friend.
  - Coxe, Richard Smith. (1792-1865). Letter: Georgetown, to Garret Wall, Trenton, NJ, 1822 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Summary: Describes his lack of political influence in Washington. Comments on the personalities of President James Monroe and John C. Calhoun. Describes the general atmosphere of the U.S. Congress. (Coxe was a New Jersey lawyer who moved to Washington, D.C. in 1822 and developed a large legal practice).
  - Cranch, William (1769-1855). Letter: Washington, DC., to Robert G. Harper, Baltimore, 1810 November 04 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Summary: Explains the judge's verdict in a legal case involving the Marine Insurance Company of Alexandria, to Harper, a Baltimore lawyer and former representative from South Carolina. (Cranch was the Chief Justice of the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia, 1805-1855).
  - Cranch, William (1769-1855). Letter: Washington, DC, to the New North Society, Boston, 1830 September 03 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Summary: Ms signed by Cranch and two others, as Committee of Management of the First Unitarian Church in the city of Washington. Invites representatives to the ordination of their new pastor, Cazneau Palfrey.
  - Cunningham, William. The Washingtonian: holograph, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Summary: Prospectus for a semi-weekly newspaper of political thought.
  - Custis, George Washington Parke (1781-1857). Letter: Alexandria, DC, to R.B. Taney, 1834 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Summary: Asks Taney's help in receiving compensation for fisheries destroyed on his property, caused by dredging the Potomac River to improve Georgetown navigation. (Custis was a playwright and the step-grandson of George Washington).
  - Cutler, Manasseh (1742-1823). Letter: Washington, to [Jedidiah] Morse, Charlestown, Mass., 1802 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    General
    Holograph signed. Mentions the opening of Congress. Asks Morse to forward a religious pamphlet. Speaks disparagingly of writings of Thomas Paine.
  - Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton (1825-1898). Letter: to Mr. Harvey, 1871 February 05 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Summary: Concerns her article on the social status of women. (Dahlgren was a Washington author).
  - Davenport, Braxton. Letter of Republicans rest, to Jeremy Robinson, Wash. City, 1822 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Summary: Welcomes his friend back to Washington; praises Robinson's selection of an attractive widow as a friend.
  - De Cow, Rachel. Letter: Washington, to unidentified recipient, 1813 September 05 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Summary: Thanks recipient for sending a check; requests he sell a property for her; mentions her brother's financial difficulties in raising a large family.
  - Dickins, Asbury (1780-1861). Letter: Washington, to Hyde de Neuville, 1819 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Summary: Informs the recipient he has been elected a resident member of the Columbian Institute in Washington, D.C. (Dickins was a secretary of the U.S. Senate in Washington, D.C. and a secretary of the Columbian Institute).
  - Douglass, Frederick (1817-1895). Letter: Washington, DC, to B.F. Underwood, 1884 May 09 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Summary: Is arranging to send a copy of his autobiography; is an interested reader of the Index, of which Underwood is editor. (Douglass was born a slave and later became an American diplomat and journalist).
  - Ellicott, Andrew (1754-1820). Letter: to the President and Directors of the Office of Discount and Deposit, 1820 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Summary: Asks to postpone for six months the payment of a note. (Ellicott was a surveyor and mathematician, who drew up early maps of the District of Columbia).
  - Fendall, Phillip Ricard (1794-1868). Letter: Washington, to Daniel Webster, 1841 July 06 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Summary: Accepts from Webster, Secretary of State, the appointment as U.S. Attorney for the District of Columbia. (Fendall was a Washington lawyer and U.S. Attorney for the District of Columbia).
  - Fendall, Phillip Ricard (1794-1868). Letter: Washington, to Henry Clay, 1849 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Summary: Forwards the proceeds of a claim from Col. Morrison's estate on Columbian College (now George Washington University); hopes Clay is recovered from recent illness and accident.
  - Force, Peter (1790-1868). Letter: Washington, to P.R. Fendall, Baltimore, 1824 May 06 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Summary: Has attended to requests Fendall made. (Force was an historian, a public printer and mayor of Washington).
  - Force, Peter (1790-1868). Letter: to P.R. Fendall, Alexandria, 1829 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Summary: Mentions that a delegation from Baltimore will be arriving to see Fendall.
  - Force, Peter (1790-1868). Letter: Washington, to Charles W. Goldsborough, 1840 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Summary: Force, as mayor of Washington, sends to Goldsborough, as president of the Board of Aldermen, a list of the bills he has signed.
  - Force, Peter (1790-1868). Letter: Washington, to Rev. Joseph B. Felt, Boston, 1843 February 07 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Summary: Requests Felt to have copies made of various historical documents for sending to Force.
  - Force, Peter (1790-1868). Letter: Washington, to Manning F. Force, Mass., 1847 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Summary: Encloses a draft of money for his son at Harvard Law School; mentions an interruption in his publishing projects.
  - Forrest, Richard. Letter: Georgetown, to George Sibbald, Philadelphia, 1795 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Summary: Requests selling prices for wheat and other commodities; can fill Sibbald's sloop with them. He also comments on the health of mutual acquaintances.
  - Forrest, Uriah (1757-1805). Letter: Georgetown, to Robert Morris, 1798 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Summary: Is greatly disappointed that Morris has not yet sent some money. (Forrest was a jurist and a Congressman from Maryland, 1793-1794).
  - French, Benjamin B. (1800-1870). Letter: U.S., House of Representatives, to Dear Sir, 1845 May 09 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Summary: Encloses a printed copy of his poem "The Changes of Earth", with holograph corrections. (French was an author and the U.S. Commissioner of Public Buildings).
  - Gales, Joseph (1786-1860). Letter: to Peter Force, 1830 March 13 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Summary: Requests Force to give some copies of a report to Mr. Rush. (Gales was a journalist and mayor of Washington, 1827-1830).
  - Gales, Joseph (1786-1860). Letter: to Peter Force, Mayor's Office, 1837 January 01 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Summary: Asks for a meeting room for a convention of tobacco planters.
  - Gales Joseph (1786-1860). Letter: Washington, to B.D. Taylor, 1840 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Summary: Conveys regret to Taylor that he and his family are not be able to make a visit because of the state of the roads.
  - Gales, Joseph (1786-1860). Letter: to Thomas Ewing, 1849 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Summary: Concerns contracts for public printing.
  - Gibbons, James (1834-1921). Letter: Baltimore, to A.P. Gorman, 1892 March 18 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Summary: Writes Senator Gorman of Maryland to ask him to use his influence to increase the appropriation 09. Joseph's Asylum in Washington. (Gibbons was the Roman Catholic Archbishop of Baltimore and the second American Cardinal).
  - Gleyer, Jane. Letter: Washington City, to Maria Cox, Baltimore, 1811 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Summary: Regrets having to leave Baltimore for Washington; comments on large number of Congressmen living near her family. (Gleyer was a Washington resident).
  - Goldsborough, Charles W. (1779-1843). Letter: Georgetown, to W. Hunter, Newport, RI, 1814 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Summary: Makes application for the post of Secretary of the Senate of the U.S. to Hunter, senator from Rhode Island. (Goldsborough was a Washington politician and served as president of the Washington Board of Aldermen).
  - Green, Duff (1791-1875). Letter: Washington, to W.R. Smith, 1834 October 06 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Summary: Asks the banker Smith to discount a note signed by his brother. (Green was a businessman, a printer and a publisher for U.S. Congress, 1827-1833).
  - Green, Duff (1791-1875). Letter: Dalton, GA, to H. Maynard, 1874 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Summary: Encloses a statement in reply to a newspaper article about his bill.
  - Greenleaf, James (1765-1843). Letter: City of Washington, to Robert Watkins, GA, 1805 January 02 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Summary: Concerns a Georgia estate, the ownership of which is in doubt. Requests Watkins, a lawyer, to perform some legal work. (Greenleaf was a Washington land speculator).
  - Greenough, Horatio (1805-1852). Letter: Florence, to George Washington, Greene, Rome, 1839 January 28 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Summary: Briefly mentions Washington statue; mentions quarrel with female acquaintance. (Greenough was an American sculptor who studied art in Rome. His most famous statue is of George Washington).
  - Greenough, Horatio (1805-1852). Letter: Washington, DC, to William C. Preston, Columbia, SC, 1842 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Summary: Writes to former South Carolina Senator about proposed location of Washington statue.
  - Hagner, Peter (1772-1850). Letter: Dept. of War, to Robert Brent, Washington, 1815 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Summary: Concerns payment of an account. (Hagner was an official in the War Department accounting office and the third auditor of the U.S. Treasury, 1817-1849).
  - Hagner, Peter Valentine (1815-1893). Letter: New York, to Governor Morgan, 1861 September 09 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Summary: Relates that the Chief of Ordnance wants the use of New York state's ordnance. (Hagner was an ordnance officer in the U.S. Union Army).
  - Hagner, Peter Valentine (1815-1893). Letter: West Troy, NY, to the District Attorney, Saratoga County, 1878 September 05 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Summary: Mentions an inspection tour.
  - Harry, Richard. Letter: Washington, to Miss Wells, 1899 February 16 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Summary: Is glad she likes his writings; soon returns to New York.
  - Henry, Joseph (1797-1878). Letter: Smithsonian Institution, to unidentified recipient, 1857 April 27 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Summary: Sends his autograph. (Henry was a scientific researcher on electricity and the first secretary and director of the Smithsonian institution in Washington, D.C.).
  - Huntt, Henry (1792-1838). Document: Washington, DC, to Juan Guillaume Hyde de Neuville, 01/1819., 1819 January (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Summary: Printed document from Henry Huntt, George Bomford and Thomas Henderson, the Corresponding Committee of the Columbian Institute, requests submissions on subjects such as agriculture. (Huntt was a Washington, D.C. doctor).
  - Jeffers, Madison. Letter: to Judges of the Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, 1836 May 31 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Summary: Defends self from accusations of improper behavior in removing a suspected runaway slave from the home of the Secretary to the British legation to the United States in Washington, D.C. (Jeffers was a constable removed from his post because of the incident described above).
  - Joyce, John Alexander. (1842-1915). Love and Laughter: holograph, Louisville KY, 01/1863, 1863 January (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Summary: (Joyce was an American lawyer and author).
  - King, Horatio (1811-1897). Letter: Washington, to Lewis J. Cist, 09. Louis, MO, 1869 January 19 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Summary: Offers for sale to Cist, an autograph collector, a letter, dated 10 Dec. 1799, written by George Washington to James Anderson, concerning management of his farms. (King was an American editor, lawyer and U.S. postmaster).
  - Lancaster, Joseph (1778-1838). Letter: Borough Road, to David Hall, 1811 September 15 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Summary: Mentions the poor condition of his aged father; expresses confidence in his ability to inspire his students. (Lancaster was an English educator, who established some schools in the U.S.).
  - Lancaster, Joseph (1778-1838). Letter: Washington, to Elizabeth Lancaster, Philadelphia, 1818. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Summary: Describes his lectures in Baltimore and his intention to lecture in Congress in Washington, D.C.
  - Lancaster, Joseph (1778-1838). Letter: Washington, to William Darlington, 1821 February 26 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Summary: Sends copies of his books.
  - Latrobe, Benjamin Henry (1764-1820). Letter: Baltimore, to Langdon Cheves, Philadelphia, 1820 January 12 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Summary: Encloses for Cheves, president of the Bank of the United States, a bill from the British consul for some cement, of a type in use in England, for possible use on new Bank of the United States. (Latrobe was an American engineer and architect and designer of the restored U.S. Capitol after the War of 1812).
  - Lee, Richard Bland (1761-1827). Letter: Washington, to the President and Directors of the Branch Bank of the US at Washington, 1818 December 01 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Summary: Lists notes of his held by the bank; requests that the names of endorsers be changed. (Lee was an American statesman and served as Congressman from Virginia, 1789-1795 and 1825-1827).
  - Mackall, Louis (1867-1930). Letter: Georgetown, DC., to Hon. Judge J. Vinson, 1895 January 15 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Summary: Writes that they must assert property rights to the use of a road to their property. (Mackall was a Washington physician).
  - Mason, John (fl., 1840-1850). Letter: Washington, to Gen. H. Dearborn, Boston, 1843 July 28 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Summary: Inquires about rumors that Boston builders plan to construct houses in Washington at a cheaper rate than the Washington builders; offers help to them as he approves this project; mentions his parents' continuing good health. (John Mason was possibly the son of John Mason (1766-1843).
  - Mayo, Robert (1784-1864). Letter: Washington City, to Dr. Huntt, Board of Health, 1832 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Summary: Mayo encloses a resolution from citizens of Washington, protesting Washington Board of Health's action in excluding almost all vegetable production of the season from the Washington markets, in response to the cholera epidemic. (Mayo was an American physician and author).
  - McKean, W.S. Letter: Washington, to the Theatrical Managers of America, 1903 March 07 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Summary: Asks theater managers to donate one percent of gross receipts for April 13, 1903 to the Memorial fund; p. 2 is facsimile of letter from actor Joseph Jefferson. (McKean was the Secretary of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Association of the United States).
  - McLane, Allan (1746-1829). Letter: High 09. Coffey House, to James Mead, Philadelphia, 1814 December 03 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Summary: States his opinion that after the Battle of Bladensburg (Aug. 24, 1814), the British forces very nearly captured the U.S. President. (McLane was an American Revolutionary War soldier and Delaware official. He was also a soldier in the War of 1812).
  - McLean, John (1785-1861). Signature, not after 04/04/1861, Circa 1861 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Summary: (McLean was a U.S. Supreme Court Justice).
  - Mills, Robert (1781-1855). Letter: Philadelphia, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, 1814 January 28 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Summary: Requests that Jefferson write him a letter of recommendation to President Madison so that he may become Surveyor of Public Buildings. (Mills was an engineer and architect of the Washington Monument in Washington, D.C.).
  - Mills, Robert (1781-1855). Letter: to George Bancroft, 1845 September 16 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Summary: Writes to Bancroft, then Secretary of the Navy. Encloses sketches of facades for the War and Navy Department buildings. Describes area that will contain the Navy Department.
  - Mills, Robert (1781-1855). Letter: to Jefferson Davis, Washington, 08/1854, 1854 August (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Summary: Writes to Davis, U.S. Secretary of War, about plans for buildings for the executive branch to be built in Washington, D.C., including spaces for the Treasury Department, State Department, Navy Department, Interior Department, and others.
  - Mulledy, Thomas F. Letter: Georgetown College, to Hon. T. Burges, Washington, 1830 May 28 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Summary: Encloses statement of Burges's son's account. (Mulledy was the president of Georgetown College (now University), 1829-1837.
  - Norton, Charles A. Long Bridge: holograph, Circa 1865 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Summary: Poem memorializing Union soldiers killed in the Civil War. (Norton was a Union army soldier).
  - Ould, Robert (1820-1882). Letter: Georgetown, DC, to the Secretary of the Navy, Washington, 1855 June 25 (Box 4, Folder 5)